{"tossups": [{"question": "This man was the target of a Russian propaganda film called \u201cThe Godfather,\u201d which detailed the mysterious disappearance of opposition leader Viktar Hanchar. This leader was subjected to a EU travel ban after he evicted diplomats whose homes he seized in the Drazdy Conflict. The Jeans, or Denim Revolution failed to depose this leader after he won the third of his five terms. This leader has been dubbed the \u201clast dictator of Europe\u201d thanks to his two decade long rule from Minsk. For ten points, name this president of Belarus.", "answer": "Alexander<b> Lukashenko</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This newspaper was the first to publish the complete text of the Watergate tapes. This newspaper\u2019s mid-20th century conservative leanings were encouraged by editor Robert McCormick, who coined its motto \u201cAn American Paper for Americans\u201d. After winning a national design competition, Howells and Hood designed this newspaper\u2019s neo-Gothic headquarters in 1911. The acronym WGN, or \u201cWorld\u2019s Greatest Newspaper\u201d, was coined in honor of this newspaper, whose parent company was briefly renamed to Tronc in 2016. For ten points, name this Midwestern daily newspaper.", "answer": "<em> Chicago<b> Tribune</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One holder of this position took out controversial ads against Richard Riordan during primaries and was widely blamed for the bankruptcy of PG&E. An Armenian holder of this title helped remove Rose Bird as state Chief Justice and came to power as the beneficiary of the Bradley Effect. Another holder of this position defeated Neel Kashkari in 2014 and endorsed Gavin Newsom as his successor. For 10 points, name this gubernatorial office held by Gray Davis, George Deukmejian, and Jerry Brown.", "answer": "<b> Governor</b> of<b> California</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Anne McAneney was the only female player of this instrument in an October 2018 analysis of 22 of the world\u2019s top orchestras. These instruments don\u2019t play in the second movement of the second<em> Brandenburg</em> <em>Concerto</em> because the natural version of this instrument couldn\u2019t play in a minor key. This instrument was vastly improved in the late 18th century by Anton Weidinger\u2019s addition of keys; those keys were replaced with valves in the early 19th century. For ten points, name this highest brass instrument in the standard orchestra.", "answer": "<b> trumpet</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The name of this group was coined by George Poindexter that called them the \u201creservoir of all the petty slanders which find a place in the most degraded places in the Union.\u201d A formal \u201cparlor\u201d was replaced by this group after John Berrien and Samuel Ingram were fired. The leader of this group added Roger Taney and Martin Van Buren to it after purging supporters of John C. Calhoun. For ten points, name this group of informal advisers to Andrew Jackson.", "answer": "<b> Kitchen Cabinet</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "George Eayre led an attack along the Smoky Hill River that preceded this event. This event was led by a man who had earlier looted an enemy baggage train at Johnsons Ranch during the Battle of Glorieta Pass. Silas Soule was murdered for testifying against the perpetrators of this event. Victims of this event had earlier traveled with Edward Wynkoop to Fort Lyon, where they were instructed to wave a white flag to dissuade violence. Black Kettle and hundreds of his tribesmen were murdered by troops under John Chivington in this event. For ten points, name this 1864 massacre of Cheyenne Indians in Colorado.", "answer": "<b> Sand Creek</b> Massacre (accept<b> Chivington</b> Massacre)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "William Hicks was sent on an expedition to fight this man, though he lost at the Battle of El Obeid. This man lived on Aba Island with his followers, where he won a victory which he compared to the Battle of Badr. The River Column was sent to relieve a general besieged by this leader, and later this man\u2019s forces were raked down by Herbert Kitchener\u2019s expedition at the Battle of Omdurman. For ten points, name this\u201cGuided One\u201d, a Muslim who was proclaimed to be a messianic redeemer in a namesake Sudanese revolt.", "answer": "<b> Mahdi</b> (or Muhammad<b> Ahmad</b> bin Abd Allah)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this country, Thomas Henry Burke was accompanying Lord Frederick Cavendish when they were attacked by several assassins with knives including Tim Kelly and Joe Brady. The Invincibles operated from this country where they committed the Phoenix Park Murders during a period called the Land War. William O\u2019Shea negotiated the Kilmainham Treaty signed by Charles Parnell in this country. For ten points, name this country where many Catholic tenants in County Mayo [my-oh] opposed wealthy English landowners.", "answer": "<b> Ireland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The first chapter of this organization was founded in Fredonia, New York, and its co-founders included Oliver Kelley and William Ireland. This organization claimed to have created the ida of Rural Free Delivery and Farm Credit. In<em> Munn v. Illinois</em>, this organization put pressure on Illinois to lower storage rates on agricultural products, a decision which was reversed in the<em> Wabash</em> case. For ten points, name this rural advocacy group with an agricultural focus.", "answer": "The<b> Grange</b> (or<b> National Grange of the Order of Patrons of Husbandry</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A poem set in this war introduces the author\u2019s Aunt Pauline as a machine tending to wounded soldiers and is titled \u201cThe Work.\u201d One poet laments an afflicted country\u2019s \u201cruined silver spires\u201d while performing humanitarian work during this war. Another poet asks \u201cwhat passing-bells for these who die as cattle\u201dand describes blood \u201cgargling from the froth-corrupted lungs\u201d in another poem set during this war. For ten points, name this worldwide conflict described in Wilfred Owen\u2019s \u201cAnthem for Doomed Youth\u201d and\u201cDulce et Decorum Est.\u201d", "answer": "<b> W</b>orld<b> W</b>ar<b> One</b> (or equivalents, accept<b> Great War</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "One ruler of this name appointed Nestorius as Archbishop of Constantinople. Another ruler of this name defeated usurper Magnus Maximus at the battle of the Save and appointed Arbogast as magister militum. Another ruler of this name built a namesake system of double walls surrounding his capital. The victor at the battle of Frigidus had this name; he was earlier made co-emperor of the East following Valens\u2019 death at Adrianople. For ten points, give this name of the last leader to have ruled both halves of the Roman empire.", "answer": "<b> Theodosius</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The discovery of this phenomena offered evidence supporting the nucleosynthesis model proposed in the \u201cAlpher-Bethe-Gammow\u201d paper. Rashid Sunyaev and Yakov Zeldovich showed that this phenomenon could be distorted by galactic clusters. Discovered using Bell Labs\u2019 Holmdel Horn Antenna, this phenomenon was later quantified by the KOBE and WMAP satellites. Arno Penzias and Robert Wilson were awarded the 1978 Nobel Prize in Physics for the discovery of, for ten points, this blackbody radiation originating from the Big Bang.", "answer": "<b> CMBR</b> (or<b> Cosmic Microwave Background Radiation</b>)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "During one scandal, this man was satirized in a cartoon as trampling a weeping woman while asking,\u201cSend me another $10,000.\u201d This man, who introduced high tariffs as part of his National Policy formed a Great Coalition with George Brown and George \u00b4Etienne Cartier. This man\u2019s ministry faced Louis Riel\u2019s Red River Rebellion and was ended by a scandal where this man\u2019s Conservative government took bribes to build a railway to British Columbia. Succeeded by Alexander Mackenzie, for ten points, name this first Prime Minister of Canada.", "answer": "Sir John Alexander<b> Macdonald</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A ruler of this kingdom was so interested in his realm\u2019s revenues that he gained the epithet \u201cnine crore Narayana.\u201d Another ruler of this kingdom established a Jacobin club</b> <b>and suffered a crippling naval defeat at (+)</b> <b>Mangalore. This kingdom used rockets to</b> <b>devastating effect during the Battle of Pollilur, prompting Eyre Coote to intervene in a war against this kingdom. Aided by the Marathas, Charles (*) </b> Cornwallis captured this kingdom\u2019s capital Srirangapatna, killing its ruler Tipu Sultan. For ten points, what South Indian kingdom that fought four wars with the British East Indian Company?", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Mysore</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>During this event, a gloomy sign warning drivers to \u201cturn left or get shot\u201d was placed in the middle of an intersection. Alvin Poussaint argued that the overturning of the (+) Rumford Fair Housing Act by Proposition 14 contributed to the outbreak of this event. The McCone Report offered ways to improve (*)</b> police-community relations after police chief William Parker compared this event\u2019s participants to \u201cmonkeys in a zoo\u201d. The roadside arrest of Marquette Frye and the subsequent brawl directly triggered this event. For ten points, name this summer 1965 race riot that occurred in a namesake Los Angeles neighborhood.", "answer": "<b> Watts</b> Riots (accept<b> L</b>os<b> A</b>ngeles race<b> riot</b>s of 19<b>65</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Ambassador Sam Sary tried to topple his nation\u2019s government in a plot named for this city. Dap Chuon was shot in a failed plot named for this city to take over the Cambodian government which inspired King Norodom Sihanouk\u2019s film</b><em><b> Shadow over Angkor</b></em><b>. In this</b> <b>city, students rose up in the 1973 (+)</b> <b>\u201cDay of Sorrow,\u201d while it also was the site of the</b> <b>Black May and Thammasat University Uprisings. In 1932, the Promoters rose up to end a dynasty that ruled from this city, the (*) </b> Chakri. For ten points, name this city, founded on the Chao Phraya River, the current capital of Thailand.", "answer": "<b> Bangkok</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Abbasid-era Iraqi artisans decorated pottery with glazes of this color, which was also on Japanese</b><em><b> sometsuke</b></em><b>. The Kraak style included flashy decorations in this color designed for</b> <b>export to Europe. Sinuous plant motifs in this color are characteristic of (+)</b> <b>Jingdezhen</b> <b>Ware, which used pigments made from imported Persian cobalt, making this color most durable to high firing temperatures. European (*)</b> Delftware imitated imported Asian designs by using decorations in this color. For ten points, what color and white name a style of porcelain, originally decorated to imitate lapis lazuli?", "answer": "<b> blue</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>John Bradstreet led a rogue expedition during this conflict, during which he slashed a peace belt to pieces. During this war, a supply column was destroyed at Point Pelee while</b> <b>George Campbell\u2019s unit was massacred at (+)</b> <b>Devil\u2019s Hole. Henry Bouquet\u2019s victory at</b> <b>this war\u2019s battle of Bushy Run relieved the siege of Fort Pitt, during which smallpox-ridden blankets were distributed. The Paxton (*) </b> Boys committed the Conestoga Massacre during this rebellion, which was largely centered on the failed siege of Fort Detroit. For ten points, name this 1763 uprising around the Great Lakes, led by a namesake Ottawa chief.", "answer": "<b> Pontiac</b>\u2019s Rebellion (accept \u201crevolt\u201d, \u201cuprising\u201d, \u201cwar\u201d, etc. for \u201crebellion\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One work which helped define this movement criticized its preceding architectural style\u2019s emphasis on form and volume and studied the emphasis of decorative signing in its title city\u2019s Strip; that work by Robert Venturi was (+)</b><em><b> Learning from Las Vegas</b></em><b>. This movement was analyzed as a rejection of historical norms in favor of commodified \u201cpastiche\u201d in a book subtitled \u201cThe Cultural Logic of Late Capitalism\u201d by Frederic (*)</b> Jameson. This movement\u2019s skepticism of historical \u201cmetanarratives\u201d was termed its namesake \u201ccondition\u201d by Jean-Francois Lyotard. For ten points, name this intellectual and cultural movement, a reaction against modernism.", "answer": "<b> postmodernism</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>Bernt Balchen cast doubt on this man\u2019s achievements, which may be marred by erased sextant measurements and claims of data that was reported to within 1\u201d, an accuracy not possible at the time. This man planned the flight path for the Navy\u2019s 1919 transatlantic</b> <b>crossing. On the (+)</b> <em><b>Josephine Ford</b></em><b>, this man travelled with Floyd Bennett, leading to</b> <b>congratulations by Calvin Coolidge. On the Ross Ice Shelf, this man built a base called (*)</b> \u201cLittle America\u201d, and he led Operation Highjump to the Antarctic. This man\u2019s brother Harry led a conservative coalition as part of a namesake \u201cOrganization\u201d in the Senate. For ten points, name this American explorer who claimed to be the first to reach the North and South Poles by air.", "answer": "Rear Admiral Richard Evelyn<b> Byrd</b> Jr. <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>A member of this profession married Maria Cresap, was the chief opponent</b> <b>of the Virginia Plan who hailed from Maryland, and died in the home of his close</b> <b>friend Aaron Burr. Luther Martin had this profession, as did (+) Andrew Hamilton</b> <b>and William Smith, two of the strongest supporters of John Peter Zenger. Prior</b> <b>to entering politics, John Adams held this occupation, in which he secured the (*)</b> freedom of Thomas Preston after the Boston Massacre. For ten points, name this occupation by which Daniel Webster argued before the Supreme Court. ANSWER:<b> lawyer</b> (accept anything mentioning the<b> law</b>; accept<b> attorney</b>; do not accept or prompt on \u201cAttorney General\u201d; prompt on \u201cjudge\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}